So these kinds of problems this is a very,
very simplified version of
what our call with the statistics literature
has bandit problems.
I said you know why they are called bandit
problems
you know this, Deepak no, 01 you written enough
of lab meetings to know these things anyway
so people know what a one-armed bandit is
come on man anyway so one-armed bandit is
a slot machine, you know what is slot machines
are you put a coin there then you pull a lever
right, and then what it does it steals your
money basically and all of that is mumbo jumbo
you know of course all of you must realize
that no casino is going to put up a machine
that actually makes money for the customer,
right.
So in the long run the slot machine will steal
your money and then you just keep pulling
that thing so that lever that you pull is
called the arm and since it has one lever
is called the one-armed bandit because it
steals your money this is one arm bandit.
So here this is very similar to the slot machine
except that instead of having one arm it has
n arms, right so each time you pull an arm
you get some kind of a pay off right and we
want to really complete the Bandit analogy.
So every time you need to pull an arm we have
to pay one rupee, right sometimes you get
back one rupee sometimes you get back nothing
that way you know that is certainly stealing
your money it is something like that, right.
So but that is essentially why it is called
a bandit problem sometimes it is also called
the multi armed bandits, right so it is called
multi on bandits because well it has multiple
arms right and the dynamics is very similar
to a slot machine, right.
Now we know I kept calling actions as arms,
right so because the literature typically
talks about arms on a bandit right, but it
is really for us we do not have to worry about
the Bandit connections so then it is essentially
this actions, right okay any questions so
far.
There are many, many ways in which you can
solve this multi-armed bandit problems right,
but the cracks here is always that you'll
have to be balancing the exploration versus
exploitation, right.
So I will talk about multiple solution concepts
right, what do we mean when we say i want
to solve a multi-armed bandit problem, right.
So one solution concept, right is asymptotic
correctness so what do I mean by that I do
not put any bounds on you or anything right
here is this multi-armed bandit problem so
give me a guarantee that eventually you will
be selecting the arm which has the highest
payoff, right T tends to infinity you will
be selecting the arm that has the highest
payoff so that is called asymptotic correctness,
right.
So this is one way of solving it a lot of
the older literature on bandit problems essentially
concern themselves with asymptotic correctness
and then of course they had some results on
things like rates of convergence and so on
so how quickly you reach the guarantee and
so on so forth, but by enlarge the analysis
was on asymptotic correctness they come up
with very simple algorithms and then you show
that the asymptotically they will converge
to the right arm, right.
So this is a one kind of thing right, the
second a popular solution concept is essentially
known as regret optimality suppose I knew
right, suppose I knew from time 0 which is
the best arm right, suppose I knew from the
beginning what is the best term to pull later
and I keep pulling the arm over and over and
over again right and I keep repeating this
experiment multiple times what will be my
expected payoff so this is time, expected
payoff it is going to be some kind of a flat
line, right.
So that is possibly the best expected payoff
that I can achieve right because I know from
the beginning I know what I see right arm,
right but since I do not know this I have
to do this exploration, right to figure out
which is the right arm right so my payoff
will look something like this right, over
time it will and eventually reach that right
as time becomes so may T foes to infinity
I will eventually reach that point, right.
So now this reward that you see here right,
this is what I could have got if I had known
the right answer from the beginning, right
so this is in some sense a loss that I incurred
because of my learning process right, so this
is sometimes colorfully referred to as a regret
so I say like well as if I had known this
from the beginning you know I would have done
so much better so this is regret.
So another way of thinking about regret is
that I am trying to maximize the total reward
that I obtained okay, not just the asymptotically
the payoff right, even during the learning
I need to get as much pay off as possible
right.
So ideally I would want this slope to be pretty
steamed right, if the slope is very steep
so what will happen is this area will come
down right, if the slope is very steep this
area is going to come down.
But what is the trade-off typically you will
have to give up is it will take a longer time
to reach optimality usually there is a trade-off
right, because you typically to do this right
you will be giving up some amount of exploration
right, so there are some corner cases where
you might actually miss out on important exploration
because you are trying to be very optimistic
with respect to the surrogate thing right
so I want it to be I want to have very little
regret so what my what I am at end up doing
is I met miss out on certain key exploration
that I should have done.
So essentially what will happen is so in some
cases I will never reach optimality also because
I would have ignored certain important outcomes
along the way so this is the trade-off that
you have to worry about.
But regret optimality is essentially looking
at how steeply you learn at the outside of
course that does not mean I can be really
bad right I mean does it have a small regret
right, but I did learn very fast I actually
went up the y-axis right but then I am going
to incorrect a constant very, very large constant
regret okay.
So that is no so you have to balance it right,
so because you keep accumulating even though
this is reached here but you still keep accumulating
regret right, so it is not it come to the
optimal case in fact we know that no algorithm
can guarantee that your regret will grow small,
I mean essentially regret will fall right,
faster than log T so it has to grow at least
test log T right, suppose you have taken T
times steps the regret you have accumulated
till that point will be proportional to log
T, right.
So and as T becomes larger the rate of growth
will become smaller and smaller right but
that is the best rate of growth that you can
achieve all that you can fiddle play around
with this some a times log T will be the rate
right, so that a is what you can fiddle around
with so those constants you can fiddle around
with but log T itself is non-negotiable so
there are results that show that log T is
a lower bound so you cannot do better than
log T in achieving regret, right.
So the essentially so if you think of this
area above this curve and between this dotted
line in this curve so that area will keep
growing at some rate right, as T becomes larger
and larger that area keeps growing at some
rate so the rate at which it will grow will
be at least log T, so that is the result that
we have, so I am not going to show you that
result but I will talk about a couple of other
things okay, so is it clear so people understand
what regret is right, good.
So third thing that I want to talk about is
what is called
PAC optimality right, or not is not I should
not say we call it PAC optimality but it should
be more PAC complexity right, so it is a little
tricky thing.
So PAC stands for probably approximately correct,
okay sometimes in a very loose fashion we
tend to use these as interchangeable things
yeah, he probably right and he is approximately
right, right so but they are not interchangeable
in the very different context very, very different
things and he say somebody is probably right
that means he is either right or wrong okay,
so he is right with some probability and he
is wrong with some probability right.
When he say somebody is approximately right
is almost surely not right, right but he is
very close to being right this is essentially
what approximately means, so it turns out
that both of these concepts are applicable
in the Bandit setting.
So when I say somebody is approximately right
in the Bandit setting what do I mean that
I give you an arm right, finally you know
what is the goal at the end of the day I am
supposed to give you an arm back, right and
this is supposed to have the highest expected
payoff.
When they say I am approximately right that
means that arm I am going to return to you
will be very close in pay off to the best
possible suppose arm, right.
Suppose I return some A to you so Q*(a) will
be very close to see Q*(a*) which is the best
arm, right is it make sense so I will return
some arm a to you at the end of my algorithm
Q*(a) will be very, very close to Q*(a*) that
what is Q* again the true expected payoff
which I do not know about right, the algorithm
des not know what Q* is but it will return
an arm and the guarantee I give you is the
Q* of that arm the unknown Q* of the top will
be close to the Q* of the best arm, okay this
is approximately correct okay.
So what is the probability connect path here,
no it is either approximately correct or not,
because we already only guaranteeing you approximately
correct guarantees right, so with a very high
probability it is approximately correct, right
it is some small probability it might give
you an arm that is more than some distance
away from the best arm yeah that is what PAC
is probably approximately correct.
Oh, I say okay, probably correct would mean
yeah or two is an optimal or not optimal yeah
probably approximately correct is well with
some probability you are approximately correct
some probability you are not, right so typically
there are many ways in which people talk about
this there is a 1 popular way of specifying
this is called the epsilon delta PAC where
epsilon refers to the approximately part and
the Delta refers to the probability part right.
So with probability of 1-? okay, the solution
I returned to you will be within e of the
best arm right, so this essentially means
probability that probability that q*(a) that
is arm written to you is greater than that
is one way of writing it but that is not what
the PAC framework guarantees, okay.
So what are the difference between the first
one and this one that is the first one was
relative guarantee this one is absolute guarantee,
so we could think of either way we can think
of absolute guarantee or related as a relative
guarantee but this is essentially what PAC
optimality means right, so for a given epsilon
delta if i can give that guarantee and then
you say there is PAC optimal for this.
But what is the interesting part here right,
if you allow you to draw an infinite number
of samples from the arms right, I can always
guarantee this they given give me whatever
epsilon delta I want i can just keep drawing
arms okay, then I some point I can say okay
now I have satisfied this okay.
The optimality part comes in when you want
to minimize the sample complexity right, so
given an epsilon and Delta what is the smallest
number of times I have to select arms says
that I can give you that epsilon delta PAC
guarantee, okay does it make sense.
So that is essentially what we are looking
at here, so this is a sample complexity question
that this is a the correctness question right,
this is a kind of rate of convergence question
and this is a sample complexity equation so
these are all slightly different notions of
solutions when I say you are solving a bandit
problem these are different notions of solutions
and the kind of algorithms that you come up
with for addressing each of these questions
would be pretty different.
You do not know but I give you the guarantee
this is the, if you know q*a* then this will
be as close as that.
Exactly so these are questions that we will
look at as we go along I have not told you
what the image is telling you what the solution
concepts are right I am not even told you
how you actually solve these problems right
so when we look at those I will tell you how
to go about doing this.
In fact it will turn out that the algorithms
themselves are very simple okay, but to analyze
it to show that this kind of guarantee holds
is where all that took place.